在我们深入研究这整个事情之前，这一切都很好。
Before we go too much further into this whole thing, this is all well and good.
但是你如何测试这个？
But how do you test this?
[笑] 我的意思是，这只是一堆任务，对吧？
[LAUGH] I mean, like it's just a bunch of tasks, right?
他们实际上是在阅读标准，这不是很好。
And they're literally reading the standard out, and that's not great.
因此，为此，我觉得我们刚刚学习了自由 monad。
And so, for this, I feel like we just learned free monads.
我觉得这是这个特定应用程序的一个很好的解决方案。
And I felt like that was a great solution to this particular app.
这样我们就可以将这些交互视为数据结构和
So that we can treat these interactions as data structures and
然后用我们想要的任何解释器来解释它们。
then interpret them with whatever interpreter we want.
通过测试解释器或实时控制台解释器。
Via either a test interpreter or a live console interpreter.
因此，这将使我们在环境中具有可测试性和可移植性。
So that'll gain us testability and portability in environments.
好的，要做到这一点，我们必须做出一些改变。
Okay, so to do this, we have to make some changes.
这些变化是，我们要考虑的影响。
These changes are, we have to think about the effects.
现在我们不只是把所有事情都放在任务中，对吧？
Now we're not just throwing everything in task, right?
这里的一切都只是任务任务任务任务任务。
Everything here is just task task task task task.
如果我们有这些具体的行动，那就更好了
And what would be better is if we had these specific actions that
我们正在捕获，就像我们对 HTTP GET 所做的一样。
we're capturing, just like we did with HTTP GET.
那些可能只是任务，但是
Those could just be task, but
我们要做的是将它们转化为代表动作的数据类型。
what we're gonna do is turn those into data types that represent the actions.
那么我们将在这里用打印做什么。
So what we'll do here with print.
我想改变字打印，但
I wanna change the word print, but
让我们首先引入liftF，我们需要它。
let's first bring in liftF, we need that.
所以我们将免费提供，
So we'll do that from free,
LiftF 来自免费，你在吗？
liftF comes from free, are you there?
你有空吗？
Are you there free?
是我，布莱恩。
It's me, Brian.
在这里的某个地方，我们会弄清楚的。
Somewhere in here, we'll figure it out.
我可能必须跳出一个文件夹才能找到它。
I probably have to jump out of a folder to get to it.
你在吗？
Are you there?
我可能毁了我的建议，我们会知道的。
I probably ruined my suggestions, we'll find out.
好的，可能在 lib 中，我假设它在 lib 中。
Okay, might be in lib, I'm assuming it's in lib.
但是我们有liftF。
But so we have liftF.
注意，把东西变成自由的 monad。
Note, turn things into free monads.
让我们引入我们的 daggy 或 taggedSum。
Let's bring in our daggy or taggedSum.
太好了，所以我们将制作用于读取和写入控制台的类型。
Great, so we'll make type for reading and writing to the console.
我们将其称为控制台，对吗？
We'll call it Console, right?
这将有不同的解释。
And this will be interpreted in different ways.
我们将为数据库做另一个。
And we'll do another one for the database.
这是该计划中的两个主要影响。
Those are two primary effects in this program.
而不必在我们的代码中担心这一点
And instead of having to worry about that in our code and
只需抛出所有任务，我们会将其视为数据结构。
just throw everything tasks, we're gonna treat it like a data structure.
所以 taggedSum ，我们将调用这个控制台。
So taggedSum and we'll call this Console.
taggedSum 在这里使用它的名字而不是试图推断它，所以
taggedSum takes it's name here instead of trying to infer it, so
作为第一个论点。
as the first argument.
然后我们会说我们有一个问题，也许。
And then we'll say we have a question, perhaps.
这需要字符串或 q 怎么样。
That takes the string or how about a q.
原来这些并不重要，这些名字。
Turns out these don't really matter, these names.
我的意思是，它有利于检查，但是当你进行变形时，
I mean, it's good for inspection, but when you do your catamorphism,
他们只是解构类型，你可以随意命名它。
they just destructure the type and you can name this whatever you want.
所以不要为此睡太多觉。
So don't lose too much sleep over that.
然后我们会做 print 和 print 会带一个字符串，太棒了。
And then we'll do print and print will take a string, terrific.
q 和 s，真正的函数式程序员编写不可能的变量，正如你所知。
q and s, true functional programmers write impossible variables, just so you know.
[笑] 如果我在工作中这样做，我会把它全部写出来。
[LAUGH] If I was doing this at work, I would write it all out.
[笑] 所以 Db，我们会做 Db 和
[LAUGH] So Db, we'll do Db and
我们在哪里得到一个保存，对吧？
where we get a Save, right?
这需要一张桌子和一条记录。
And that takes a table and a record.
所有人，离开这里，
And All, get out of here,
All 需要表和查询。
All takes the table and a query.
我选择传入 where 子句，所以我们之前没有看到，
I made it optional to pass the where clause in so we didn't see that earlier,
但确实如此。
but it does.
好的，很酷，所以我们有这两个。
Okay, cool, so we have these two.
关于自由 monad，我没有提到的一件事是
One thing I didn't mention about a free monad is that
它实际上希望将函子 [LAUGH] 传递给它。
it actually expects functors [LAUGH] to be passed to it.
我们应该制作这些函子。
We should be making these functors.
但是你实际上可以把任何东西都变成一个完整的东西，
But you can actually make anything into a functor with whole thing,
别担心。
don't worry about it.
我只想喊出来。
I just want to call it out.
[笑] 好的，所以，Console，Db，两种数据类型将代表我们的函数。
[LAUGH] All right, so, Console, Db, two data types gonna represent our functions.
所以现在我们必须进入我们有打印的功能。
So now we have to go into our functions where we have print.
而不是实际打印，让我们在这里做 realPrint，对吗？
And instead of actually printing, let's do realPrint here, right?
我们将制作一个打印功能，它只是简单地做那个liftF 废话，对吧？
And we'll make a print function that simply does that liftF nonsense, right?
LiftF，我们将构建我们的 Console.Print 和
liftF and we'll construct our Console.Print and
我们将把字符串传递给它。
we'll pass the string to it.
我们的问题功能也是如此。
Likewise with our question function.
我想我们在这里称它为 getInput。
I think we called it getInput here.
所以我们只是要在这里调用 print 和 question 来制作数据类型。
So we're just gonna call print and question here to make the data types.
然后当我们解释它时，我们将调用真正的函数。
And then when we interpret it, we'll call the real functions.
所以我们可以将它们与 realPrint 和 getInput 放在一起。
So we could put those together with realPrint and getInput.
也许我们称之为写输出，我不知道，writeOutput [LAUGH] 看起来很棒。
Maybe we call it write output, I don't know, writeOutput [LAUGH] looks great.
现在有人有任何问题吗？
Does anybody have any questions at this point?
我们只是通过免费提供东西的动作。
We're just going through the motions of putting stuff in free.
但是现在我们有了这两个。
But now we have these two.
我们必须为所有人做同样的事情，
We've got to do the exact same thing for All,
我们将其称为 dbAll 和 dbSave。
we'll call it dbAll and dbSave.
这将是 Db.All，这很无聊。
This will be Db.All, this is rather boring.
大多数这些东西只是从定义和
Most of this stuff just follows from the definitions and
你只是在填空，对吗？
you're just filling in the blanks, right?
表，查询，表，查询。
Table, query, table, query.
然后你有 Db.Save(table, record)。
Then you have Db.Save(table, record).
我们拿走我们的桌子和我们的记录。
And we take our table and our record.
再一次，我可以自动化所有这些。
And again, I could have automated all of this.
它只是类型的组合，这实际上只是
It's just composition of the type, this is literally just
由dbAll和liftF组成，对吗？
composed dbAll and liftF, right?
即便如此，我也不必每次都写出来。
And even then I don't have to write that out every time.
但我这样做是为了
But I'm doing this for
完整性的缘故，所以你可以看到因为很多这有点令人困惑。
completeness' sake and so you can see cuz a lot of this is kinda confusing.
好吧，太好了，现在会发生什么？
All right, great, now what happens?
[笑] 好吧，我们必须在这些地方将其切换到 dbAll 和 dbSave。
[LAUGH] Well we gotta switch this to dbAll and dbSave in these places.
我可能应该刚刚重命名原件，但你活着，你学习。
I probably should have just renamed the originals, but you live, you learn.
现在这将是一个问题，一个问题，一个问题。
And this is now going to be question, question, question.
如果我错过任何一个，我会很快，[笑]所以让我们看看。
If I miss any, I'm going real fast, [LAUGH] so let's see.
因为这并不有趣，我只是在更新功能
Cuz this is not interesting, I'm just updating the functions
我一开始就不应该重命名。
that I should not have renamed in the first place.
dbAll，很酷，认为我们做到了。
dbAll, cool, think we did it.
我们做到了吗，dbSave，dbAll，太棒了。
Did we do it, dbSave, dbAll, great.
那么，既然我们正在这样做，会发生什么？
So, now that we're doing this, what's gonna happen?
那么 f 返回返回一个免费的 monad，而不是一个任务。
Well f returns returns a free monad, not a task.
所以我们有解释，我们必须自由地折叠Map（解释），
So we have interpret, we have to foldMap(interpret) on the free,
我们要把它解释为一项任务。
and we're gonna interpret it to a task.
解释，解释，解释，我们如何解释？
Interpet, interpet, interpret, how do we interpret it?
好吧，就像我们之前所做的那样，我们将编写一个小解释器。
Well just like we did before, we'll write a little interpreter.
如果你曾经做过免费的 monad 事情，比如在网上查这个，这就是这里
And this is where if you ever do free monad stuff like looking this up online,
你正试图真正进入自由 monads，
you're trying to get really into free monads,
你开始处理可组合的解释器。
you start to deal with composable interpreters.
就像我有这个口译员和那个口译员一样
Like I have this interpreter and that interpreter and
我想把它们组合在一起。
I want to kind of compose them together.
当我将所有效果合成为免费时，
And as I'm composing all my effects into free, which
我刚刚将我的所有效果标准化为这个 monad，所以它们都是连锁的。
I've just normalized all my effects into this one monad so they just all chain.
现在我的问题变成了，我如何分解并传入不同的解释器？
Now my problem becomes, how do I break down and pass in different interpreters?
就目前而言，我有两个影响。
For the time being right now, I have two effects.
我不会带来副产品和
And I'm not gonna bring in co-products and
所有这些东西都是为了尝试编写解释器。
all this stuff to try to compose interpreters.
所以我们要做的是我要说，我接受这个，接受这个东西。
So what we're gonna do is I'm gonna say, I take this, take this thing.
我现在不知道这东西是控制台还是数据库，我不确定。
I don't know if this thing's a console or a DB right now, I'm not sure.
而不是试图正式化并使这更好一点，
And instead of trying to formalize and make this a little nicer,
我要继续说，嘿，你有桌子吗？
I'm just gonna go ahead and say, hey, do you have a table?
因为我知道这两个都有桌子。
Because I know that both of these have table.
所以这是，我只是在作弊，
So this is, I'm just cheating,
因为我现在不想经历这一切。
because I don't want to go through all that right now.
老实说，我认为当你有类型时，这些东西会更好。
And honestly, I think that stuff is much nicer when you have types.
并且在无类型语言中可能有更好的解决方案来组合
And there's probably better solutions in an untyped language to compose
口译员。
interpreters.
好的，所以如果你有一张桌子，那么我们会解释，
All right, so if you've got a table then we'll interpret,
这里调用dbToTask，否则调用consoleToTask。
here call dbToTask, otherwise, we'll call consoleToTask.
所以这是两个。
So these are the two.
我们将传入我们的 x。
And we'll pass in our x.
大家看到了吗？
Does everybody see?
哇，每个人都看到所有那些 x 吗？
Wow, does everybody see all those x's?
[笑] 很明显，我为什么要这样做以及那是为了什么，
[LAUGH] So obviously, why I'm doing this and what that's for,
就像我有一个 x，我不知道它是哪个。
it's like I've got an x, I don't know which one it is.
我必须将这种只是原始数据的数据类型转换为实际运行的任务。
I have to turn this data type that's just raw data into an actual running task.
而不是做任何更有趣的事情，我只会这样做。
And instead of doing anything fancier, I'll just do that.
所以 dbToTask 接受我们的 x，我们会做得很好
So dbToTask takes our x, and we'll do that nice little
catamorphism，如果我们有一个保存，我们就拿一张桌子。
catamorphism where if we have a save, we take a table.
从字面上看，这只是 dbSave [笑] 对，或者只是 Save。
And literally it's just dbSave [LAUGH] right, or it's just Save.
在我们拥有全部的地方，它只是全部。
Where we have an All, it's just All.
我们经历并重命名了我们的类型，但 Save 持有相同的参数。
We went through and renamed our types but Save is holding the same arguments.
所以它只是将它的参数传递给 save 函数。
So it's just gonna pass its arguments into the save function.
所以通常你会说，它需要一张桌子和一条记录。
So normally you'd say like, it takes a table and a record.
然后我们将继续使用表调用 save 并记录和
And then we'll go ahead and call save with the table and record and
作为任务返回。
that returns as a task.
所以我可以通过它保存。
So I could just pass it save.
看看它是如何工作的？
See how that works?
与 All 一样，我得到表和一个查询，然后它只调用 all(table,
Same thing with All, I get the table and a query and then it just calls all(table,
询问）。
query).
让我们对 consoleToTask 做同样的事情。
Let's do the same thing with the consoleToTask.
如果我有问题，我会调用 getInput。
And what's gonna happen here is if I have a question, I'm just gonna call getInput.
如果我们有打印，我们将调用 writeOutput，非常好。
And if we have a print, we'll call writeOutput, excellent.
所以我们只是映射保存我们参数的数据类型
So we're just mapping our datatypes holding our arguments
进入将与此一起运行的实际功能。
into actual functions that will run with this.
这很酷，让我们看看会发生什么。
So that's cool, let's see what happens.
我非常怀疑这会奏效。
I'm highly doubtful this is gonna work.
好吧，我是布莱恩。
All right, I'm Brian.
[笑]好吧，这里发生了什么？
[LAUGH] All right, what happens here?
我拿到了第一个。
I got the first one.
等等等等，.foldMap 不是一个函数，好吧。
Blah blah blah, .foldMap is not a function, okay.
那么这里发生了什么？
So what's happening here?
所以我们把它变成了一个任务并运行它。
So we turned it into a task and we ran it.
我们在开始时看到了这种情况。
We saw that happen with start.
我们跑了 f，它什么也没做，只是返回了一个自由的 monad。
We ran f, it did nothing but return us a free monad.
然后我们解释了实际运行问题的自由单子，
Then we interpreted that free monad which actually ran the question,
这太棒了。
which is awesome.
然后我们分叉了它，所以它实际上运行了任务并且
And then we forked that so it actually ran the task and
它返回的内容应该传递给 runApp。
what it returned should be passed in to runApp.
那么问题来了，getInput 返回了什么？
So the question is, what did getInput return?
或者抱歉，不是 getInput 返回的是什么，而是 start 返回的是什么？
Or sorry, not what did getInput return, it's what did start return?
我们将返回 menu 或 getAuthor。
We'll return menu or getAuthor.
我怀疑菜单，这些是功能，
And I have a suspicion that menu, these are functions,
所以他们必须被调用，然后他们是自由的单子。
so they have to be called and then they're free monads.
但是我们在这里调用它，让我们看看 f 是什么。
But here we're calling it, let's just see what f is.
不过，我们真的很接近，而且我们几乎没有时间做这个了。
We're real close though, and we're almost out of time for this one.
我们花了一点时间调试这个，以便我们可以弄清楚发生了什么。
We spent a little bit longer debugging this so we can figure out what's going on.
也许我们可以花一点时间来编写我们的另一个解释器。
Maybe we can take a second to write our other interpreter.
所以它说第一个 f 是这个东西，好吗？
So it says the first f is this thing, okay?
这是一个函数，好吧，我们称这个函数为
It's a function, okay, and we call that function and
我们免费得到这个，因为它调用 dbAll。
we get this free, cuz it calls dbAll.
第二个是函数
The second one is a function,
已经很有趣了
it's interesting it already
调用了两次，对吗？
called this twice, right?
发生了什么，它被称为开始，它没有任何作者。
What happened, is it called start, it didn't have any authors.
然后它过去调用createAuthor，然后
So then it went over and called createAuthor, and
然后它结束调用，执行 dbSave 然后转到菜单。
then it's ending up calling, does dbSave and then goes to menu.
dbSave 是我们想要它做的事情吗？
Is dbSave the thing that we wanted it to do?
这就是我们所说的，dbSave？
Is that what we called it, dbSave?
是的，liftF，Save，Db。
Yeah, liftF, Save, Db.
好吧，让我们再试一次，现在我们得到了什么，这里的 f 是什么？
All right, let's just try this again, now what do we get, what is f in here?
f 是 getInput，我们搞砸了。
f is getInput, we screwed up.
我们把 getInput 留在了这里。
We left the getInput in here.
那个是从哪里来的？
Where did that come from?
我忘了，它就在那里，你去吧。
I forgot, it was way up there, there you go.
这就是正在发生的事情。
So that's what's going on.
所以这里发生的事情是我们没有返回正确的类型。
So what happened here is that we didn't return the right type.
我们没有类型检查器，我没有更新，我们去了。
We don't have a type checker, I didn't update that, there we go.
好吧，让我们看看会发生什么。
All right, so let's see what happens.
我现在可以清除所有这些日志。
I can clear all these logs now.
好吧，那就跑吧，我是布赖恩。
All right, so run that, I am Brian.
你今天想去哪里？
Where do you want to go today?
我想写。
I want to write.
哇，转到标题：嗨。
Whew, go to Title: Hi.
就是这样，踢屁股。
So that's it, kick ass.
好的，所以我们正在做免费的 monad。
All right, so we're doing free monads.